Register of the Lee Roberts Pennington papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Lee Roberts Pennington papers
1909-1974
88019
Hoover Institution Archives
16 manuscript boxes (6.4 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches, reports, memoranda, serial issues, clippings, and other printed matter relating to communism and other political issues in the United States, subversive activities in the United States, and investigative activities of the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) and private organizations collected by agent Lee Roberts Pennington, who specialized in investigating radical left wing activists when employed by the FBI.
Pennington, Lee Roberts, 1894-1974.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1988.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1894 Born in Martinsburg, West Virginia
1915 Received Bachelor of Arts degree from the University of Maryland
1917-1918 Served as Lieutenant in the 60th Infantry in World War I
1920 Married Catherine Carter
1928 Began working for the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI)
1944 Served as Department Commander of the District of Columbia America Legion
1952-1954 Served as National Executive Commiteeman of the American Legion
1953 Retired from FBI
1953-1974 Believed to be employed by the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA)
1955 Became full-time Director of the American Legion's National Americanism Commission's counter-subversive activities in Washington, DC
1972 The Watergate scandal; Pennington under suspicion for destroying documents due to his connection with James W. McCord
1974 Died in Bethesda, Maryland
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection contains correspondence, speeches, reports, memoranda, serial issues, clippings, pamphlets, and other printed matter relating to communism in the United States, subversive activities in the United States, the issues surrounding Watergate, the Vietnam War, and the Middle East, and investigative activities of the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) and private organizations.
Arrangement Statement
The collection is organized into five series: Biographical File, General Correspondence, Printed Matter, Speeches and Writings, and Subject File.
American Legion. National Americanism Commission.; American Security Council.; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation.; Communism--United States.; Internal security--United States.; Subversive activities--United States.
- Biographical File, 1945-1963
  - Personal effects, 1947-1963 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Programs, 1945-1963 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- Correspondence, 1933-1974 (Box-folder 1: 3-6, Box-folder 2: 1-2)
- Printed Matter, 1909-1974
  - Bulletins, 1962 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Congressional Record, 1956-1972 (Box-folder 2: 4-6)
  - Essays, 1909-1963 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation case reports, 1933-1952 (Box-folder 3: 2-3)
  - Manuals, undated (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Memoranda, 1918-1963 (Box-folder 3: 5, Box-folder 4: 1)
  - News releases, 1962-1974 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Newspaper articles, 1939-1974
    - 1939, undated (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - 1950-1959 (Box-folder 4: 4-5)
    - 1960-1969 (Box-folder 4: 6-7, Box-folder 5: 1-5)
    - 1970-1974 (Box-folder 6: 1-4, Box-folder 7: 1-3)
  - Pamphlets, 1923-1969 (Box-folder 7: 4, Box-folder 8: 1-3)
  - Reports, 1943-1974 (Box-folder 8: 4, Box 9-11, Box-folder 12: 1-2)
  - Serial issues, 1935-1973
    - American Capsule News, 1968 (Box-folder 12: 3)
    - American Jewish Committee, 1954 (Box-folder 12: 4)
    - The American Nationalist, 1956 (Box-folder 12: 5)
    - American Security Council Newsletter, 1957-1963 (Box-folder 12: 6)
    - Auditgram, 1949 (Box-folder 12: 7)
    - Battleline, 1973 (Box-folder 12: 8)
    - Citizens Foreign Aid, 1963 (Box-folder 12: 9)
    - Civil Liberties Union News, 1963 (Box-folder 12: 10)
    - Committee Reporter, 1954 (Box-folder 12: 11)
    - Common Sense, 1957 (Box-folder 12: 12)
    - Dan Smoot Report, 1963-1973 (Box-folder 12: 13)
    - Day Magazine, 1960 (Box-folder 12: 14)
    - Dollar Hollar, 1964 (Box-folder 12: 15)
    - Facts, 1965 (Box-folder 12: 16)
    - Firing Line, 1957-1968 (Box-folder 13: 1-3)
    - Fort Lauderdale News, 1964 (Box-folder 13: 4)
    - Free Choice, 1973 (Box-folder 13: 5)
    - Free Enterprise, 1957 (Box-folder 13: 6)
    - Genealogical Society Observer, 1968 (Box-folder 13: 7)
    - Harper's, 1962 (Box-folder 13: 8)
    - Herald of Freedom, 1966-1973 (Box-folder 13: 9)
    - Householder's Newsletter, 1962 (Box-folder 13: 10)
    - Human Events, 1958-1964 (Box-folder 13: 11)
    - Inform, 1963-1973 (Box-folder 13: 12)
    - Investigator, 1935-1973 (Box-folder 14: 1)
    - Intelligence Digest, 1973 (Box-folder 14: 2)
    - Liberty, 1944 (Box-folder 14: 3)
    - National Republic, 1942-1958 (Box-folder 14: 4)
    - National Review, 1963 (Box-folder 14: 5)
    - National Right to Work News Service, 1973 (Box-folder 14: 6)
    - New Hampshire Sunday News, 1972 (Box-folder 14: 7)
    - New Republic, 1948 (Box-folder 14: 8)
    - News and Views, 1960-1967 (Box-folder 14: 9)
    - Typescript about Overseas Weekly, circa 1962 (Box-folder 14: 10)
    - Peacemaker, 1963 (Box-folder 14: 11)
    - The Pine Torch, 1963 (Box-folder 14: 12)
    - The Record, 1949 (Box-folder 14: 13)
    - Red Diamond, 1938-1963 (Box-folder 14: 14)
    - Report to America, 1963 (Box-folder 14: 15)
    - This Week, 1957 (Box-folder 14: 16)
    - Time, 1964 (Box-folder 14: 17)
    - Tocsin, 1964 (Box-folder 14: 18)
    - Today!, undated (Box-folder 14: 19)
    - Top of the News, 1961 (Box-folder 14: 20)
    - United States News and World Report, 1961-1973 (Box-folder 14: 21)
    - The Washington Report, 1961-1965 (Box-folder 14: 22)
    - Zions Herald, 1952 (Box-folder 14: 23)
  - Transcripts, 1955 (Box-folder 15: 1-3)
- Speeches and Writings, 1936-1968
  - "The Administration of Justice,", 1959 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - "Americanism and the Citizen,", undated (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - "Annual Luncheon of the Indiana Academy of General Practice,", 1951 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - "Bank Defalcations and Their Concealment,", 1953 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - Boston Conference of the National Association of Bank Auditors and Comptrollers, 1951 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - "The Challenge to Law Enforcement,", 1944 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - Chamber of Commerce, Covington, Kentucky, 1938 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - "Citizenship Today,", 1940 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - "Commencement,", undated (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - "Defalcations and Their Concealment,", 1949 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - Erie Chapter of the National Association of Cost Accountants, 1953 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - Fourty-Fourth Annual Convention of the Oklahoma Bankers Association, 1940 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - "The FBI and Its War on Crime,", 1938 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - "The FBI and the Embezzler,", 1953 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - "The FBI's National Defense Program,", 1941 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - Fulton County Police Training School, 1941 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - "How Spies Are Identified,", undated (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - "Internal Controls,", undated (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - "Investigative Accounting,", 1953 (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - "Is There a Spy Menace?,", undated (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - "Keys to Freedom,", 1963 (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - "M-Day for the FBI,", undated (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - Minnesota Bankers Convention, 1938 (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - Ohio Newspaper Association, 1962 (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - "Our National Crime Problem,", 1936 (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - "Outlaw the Vigilante!,", undated (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - "Preparedness and the FBI,", 1941 (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - "President Powers,", 1941 (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - "Problems of Law Enforcement,", 1968 (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - "Propaganda and the Antidote from the Viewpoint of the FBI,", 1942 (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - "Prophecy and Modern Israel,", 1968 (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - "The Relocation Problem,", 1943 (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - Rochester Chamber of Commerce, 1947 (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - Rotary and other civic clubs of Charlottesville, Virginia, 1940 (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - "Sabotage,", 1942 (Box-folder 16: 3)
  - "The Saboteur--How Does He Work?,", undated (Box-folder 16: 3)
  - "Spies and the Underworld,", undated (Box-folder 16: 3)
  - "True Costs of Crime,", 1936 (Box-folder 16: 3)
  - "Undermining Our National Defense,", undated (Box-folder 16: 3)
  - Uniontown, Pennsylvania, 1941 (Box-folder 16: 3)
  - Untitled, undated (Box-folder 16: 3)
  - "War Begins,", 1941 (Box-folder 16: 3)
  - Young Men's Christian Association (Y.M.C.A.) of Buffalo, New York, 1937 (Box-folder 16: 3)
  - "Your Government and Mine,", 1946 (Box-folder 16: 3)
- Subject File, 1953-1968
  - American Legion, undated (Box-folder 16: 4)
    Scope and Contents note
    Resolution, letter, and other printed matter relating to the American Legion. The American Legion is an organization founded following World War I in 1919 offering membership to veterans and honorably discharged members of the United States Armed Forces who served at least one day of active duty in major wars.
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI), 1953-1967 (Box-folder 16: 5)
    Publications, lists, articles, and other printed matter relating to the activities of the FBI.
  - Group Research, Inc., 1967-1968 (Box-folder 16: 5)
    Reports, publications, newsletters, and other printed matter relating to Group Research, Inc., a product of the Reuther Memorandum formed by Robert Kennedy to inform the liberal parties about the activities of the conservative parties. The Reuther Memorandum stated that the activities of America's radical right-wing conservative parties were injecting their harmful ideology too deeply into the American culture as a whole (such as the persecution of Communists by the House Un-American Activities Committee headed by Senator Joseph McCarthy during the Cold War period) and were thus gaining too much power and influence.